<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../_generator/doc.xslt" media="screen" ?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010-2017 BusinessCode GmbH, Germany

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<doc:Doc title="WYSIWYG exports" xmlns:doc="http://www.businesscode.de/schema/bcdui/doc-1.1.0">
  <doc:Chapter title="WYSIWYG exports" type="overview">
    <doc:Body>
      The BCD-UI contains two kinds of WYSIWYG (what-you-see-is-what-you-get) exports:
        <dl>
          <dt>Spread sheet</dt>
        <dd>Spread sheet WYSIWYG exports are useful when the exported numbers are to be used in further calculations and when beyond the core WYSIWGY
          additional numbers are requested. For example one sheet may contain the percentages shown, a second one shows the absolute values behind
          the percentages. In the web front-end these values are often shown in the tool tip.
        </dd>
        <dt>PDF</dt>
        <dd>PDF WYSIWYG exports are useful when the formatting of the report including coloring is the core requirement.</dd>
        </dl>
    </doc:Body>
    <doc:SubChapter title="Spread sheet" >
      <doc:Body>
        You can export a HTML Element and its context to a spreadsheet by specifying the HTML source and calling:
        <pre><![CDATA[bcdui.component.exports.excel.exportHTMLElement({sourceElementOrId: "myDiv"});]]></pre>
        The following picture shows a cube on the left and on the right you see this cube exported to Excel.
        <img src="wysiwyg.png"/>
      </doc:Body>
    </doc:SubChapter>
    <doc:SubChapter title="PDF" >
      <doc:Body>
        The PDF Export not only allows exporting to a PDF file but also to a image file like e.g jpg. So you can for example export whole report
        pages as pdf files or charts as images. It also allows specifying an own css file which is used only during export which allows pdf specific
        tuning of the layout and style. For more details, please consult the <a href="../../../../gendocu/api/bcduiCoreApiDoc.xml#pdfExport">pdfExport API</a>.
      </doc:Body>
    </doc:SubChapter>
  </doc:Chapter>
</doc:Doc>

