<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../_generator/doc.xslt" media="screen" ?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010-2017 BusinessCode GmbH, Germany

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<Doc title="Bootstrap" xmlns="http://www.businesscode.de/schema/bcdui/doc-1.1.0">
  <Chapter title="Overview" type="overview">
    <Body>
    </Body>

    <SubChapter title="Get the tools">
      <Body>
        To start development with BCD-UI, first get the tools:
        <ul>
          <li>Make sure you have jdk 8 or higher.</li>
          <li>Install an appropriate version of Eclipse.</li>
          <li>Install Tomcat 6.13 or higher.</li>
          <li>Add Tomcat as a server to Eclipse (New->Server->Apache->Tomcat)</li>
          <li>Make sure you have IE 11 or FireFox. (Chrome and Safari are also supported.)</li>
        </ul>
        It is possible to develop BCD-UI with other IDEs as Eclipse as well, but BCD-UI development plugins are only available for Eclipse.
        Also any other J2EE application server like Weblogic, Websphere or Oracle AS, can be used instead of tomcat.
        At the time of writing this document, the Eclipse Neon is not recommenend, because JavaScript support is not working properly.
        The Edge or older IE browser versions are only partly compatible; please contact us for details. 
        If you want to use tomcat in production, you should consider setting up the server properly.
        For performance reason you should allow compression for static resources in server.xml, 
        see <a href="https://github.com/businesscode/BCD-UI/blob/master/Server/configFiles/tomcat/server.xml">BCD-UI/Server/configFiles/tomcat/server.xml</a>
        There the compression is turned on for a list of mime/types.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
    <SubChapter title="XML catalog">
      <Body>
        Adding the XML schema catalog of BCD-UI to your workspace will support you in creating xml configuration files for BCD-UI
        using <pre>https://businesscode.github.io/BCD-UI-Docu/xsd/bcduiCatalog.xml</pre>
        <img src="xmlCatalog.png"/>
        <p>will bring you:</p>
        <img src="xmlSupport.png"/>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
    <SubChapter title="JS Libray">
      <Body>
        <p>Adding the BCD-UI Javascript Api Stubs to your workspace will support you writing JavaScript code. 
        The Javascript files can be obtained here: "ADD_LOCATION".
        In Eclipse the js stubs can be setup in Preferences/JavaScript/Include Path/User Libray. First a new library can be added. I.e. BCD-UI and afterwards
        the folder containing all stubs can be added. (Add Folder...)
        </p>
        <img src="addJsCodeCompletion.png"/>
        <p>will bring you, code completion and help tooltips while hovering with your mouse:</p>
        <img src="jsCompletion.png"/>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
    <SubChapter title="Custom Element">
      <Body>
        <p>The Eclipse IDE has a feature to allow code templates to be inserted for html files. It is possible to add the custom elements registered by BCD-UI as
        templates so that there is a kind of code completion.</p>
         <p> So first import the bcdui-templates.xml file in Preferences/Web/HTML Files/Editor/Templates. Then the elements should in the template list.</p>
         <img src="htmlTemplates.png"/>
         <p>While editing html files the templates popup can be opened with strg-space and the list of BCD-UI elements should be found as shown here:</p>
         <img src="htmlTemplates_usage.png"/>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
  </Chapter>
</Doc>