<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../_generator/doc.xslt" media="screen" ?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010-2017 BusinessCode GmbH, Germany

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<Doc title="Caching" xmlns="http://www.businesscode.de/schema/bcdui/doc-1.1.0">

  <Chapter title="Caching overview" type="overview">
    <Body>
      Caching is a mechanism to speed up performance drastically, next to database tuning it is the most important performance measure.
      BCD-UI supports caching and makes caching setup easy.
      It allows for reducing server and network load and improving user experience at the same time.
      Depending on the type of expected access different caching strategies are optimal.
      BCD-UI supports two types of caching
      <dl>
        <dt>Client side caching</dt>
        <dd>Client side caching is often the most effective way of caching.
            It prevents completely repeated requests from a client, like for static image files or often needed identical data like geo-data.
            No load at all is produced for network and server and the user sees the requested data immediately, more like in a desktop application.
            This is the best approach for repeated requests from a single client.</dd>
        <dt>Server side caching</dt>
        <dd>Server side caching use the cache on the server.
        The clients need to do an actual request but repeated identical requests from multiple clients, like default reports, are answered with low overhead.</dd>
      </dl>
    </Body>
  </Chapter>

  <Chapter title="Caching setup" type="api">
    <Body>
      The definition of when a resource expires is done identically for server and client caching.
      It is possible to define the 'expires' date of the answer for a request as a sample occurring at <code>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 12:30:40 UTC</code> in terms of
      <dl>
        <dt><code>ExpiresAbsTime</code></dt><dd> time, like "00:00:00" leading to <code>Wed, 02 Dec 2009 00:00:00 UTC</code></dd>
        <dt><code>ExpiresAbsDow</code></dt><dd> day of week incl. hour, like "Sat-12" leading to <code>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 12:00:00 UTC</code></dd>
        <dt><code>ExpiresAbsDatetime</code></dt><dd> absolute date time, like "2011-01-20 12:00:00" leading to <code>Thu, 01 Jan 2011 12:00:00 UTC</code></dd>
        <dt><code>ExpiresRelDays</code></dt><dd> number of days starting from the request, same time, like "2" leading to <code>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 12:30:40 UTC</code></dd>
        <dt><code>ExpiresRelTime</code></dt><dd> number of hours/min/sec starting from the request, like "01:00:05" leading to <code>Tue, 01 Dec 2009 13:30:45 UTC</code></dd>
        <dt><code>CacheRequestDirective</code></dt><dd> native HTTP1.1 header string to be set in Cache-Control header</dd>
      </dl>
      There can be multiple space separated values for ExpiresAbsTime and ExpiresAbsDow, like "00:00:00 12:00:00", the next matching one is used for the response expires.
      The response will have the <a href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec14.html#sec14.21">HTTP Expires</a> header be set accordingly.
    </Body>

    <SubChapter title="Disable Caching">
      <Body>
        During development, you do not usually have enable caching. For this case BCD-UI provides the possibility to enable/disable all caching settings.
        To achieve this please define a environment entry within your context.xml file with the name: "bcdui/disableCache" like this:
        <xml>
         <Environment name="bcdui/disableCache" type="java.lang.Boolean" value="true"/>
        </xml>
        This does not only apply to the server and client side caching described here but also to the caching of <a href="../binding/doc.xml">Bindings</a>.
        RequestLifecycleFilter will send a Cache-Control: no-cache; no-store for all resources if set to true.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
  </Chapter>


  <Chapter title="Client side caching" type="api">
    <Body>
      Client side caching is by far the most efficient way of caching in most cases.
      BCD-UI's ClientCachingFilter is responsible for adding caching information to the HTTP response.
      Client filters also allow an ExcludeUrls parameter with a space separated list of regular expressions.
      If an expression matches the request path, the filter takes no action.
    </Body>

    <SubChapter title="ClientCachingFilter">
      <Body>
        The following defaults are added to web.xml
        <xml>
          <filter>
            <filter-class>de.businesscode.soa.web.cacheControl.ClientCachingFilter</filter-class>
            <filter-name>DefaultClientCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <init-param>
              <param-name>ExtensionsRestriction</param-name>
              <param-value>gif jpg png css xslt</param-value>
            </init-param>
            <init-param>
              <param-name>ExpiresAbsTime</param-name>
              <param-value>00:00:00</param-value>
            </init-param>
            <init-param>
              <param-name>ExcludeUrls</param-name>
              <param-value>/private/</param-value>
            </init-param>
          </filter>
          <filter-mapping>
            <filter-name>DefaultClientCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
          </filter-mapping>
        </xml>

        Sometimes even the browser-build in caching needs to be disabled.
        This can be either because it can be changed at any moment in the data base
        or because the content produced by the server depends on a server session value like user or language.
        This can be achieved by adding the following to web.xml
        <xml>
          <filter>
            <filter-class>de.businesscode.soa.web.cacheControl.ClientCachingFilter</filter-class>
            <filter-name>NoClientCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <init-param>
              <param-name>CacheRequestDirective</param-name>
              <param-value>no-cache; no-store</param-value>
            </init-param>
          </filter>
          <filter-mapping>
            <filter-name>NoClientCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <url-pattern>/userRights</url-pattern>
          </filter-mapping>
        </xml>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Client side JSP carrier page caching">
      <Body>
        To enable caching of jsp carrier pages it is important not to make the produced content dependent
        on server side values, which are not included in the parameter like implicit user rights.
        BCD-UI assures that client side status like filter settings or tab status is not transferred as a parameter but rather as a anchor, not conflicting with caching.
        Developers need to assure that links within the application follow the same pattern for example by using the appropriate link builder tag.
        In most cases, only language and the user-rights will be parameters controlling the server side page producing.
        If it is required to control HTML content with information other than parameters, for example server session information,
        exclude jsp page from caching or see user token below.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Client side caching of static files">
      <Body>
        Static files can usually be cached. How long depends on when a re-deployment may happen.
        Typically if deployments happen over the week-end, set <code>ExpiresAbsDow</code> to 'Sat' as shown above.
        To identify static files it is possible to define for which extensions the ClientCachingFilter applies via ExtensionsRestriction.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Client side static data caching">
      <Body>
        In a reporting environment, reporting and reference data can often be cached until the next morning.
        This is supported by setting <code>ExpiresAbsTime</code> to '07:00:00'.
        To support different caching times for different data, create different servlet instances at these URLs.
        User dependent data is to be excluded from the caching. If caching should be enabled, see User token below.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="User token">
      <Body>
        The user token consists of the userid plus the last modification timestamp of the user profile. It is added to all data requests from BCD-UI behind the scenes.
        Since the browser uses the cache only for recurrent requests with the same URL changing the user token will lead to a new server request.
        Every property change, influencing the response of the server independent of the request parameters, must change the last-modified of the user profile.
        This can be, for example, a change in user rights or preferred language.
        <p/>
        Usage of default items in <a href="../binding/doc.xml">Bindings</a>, for example for row-level-security or language setting,
        requires that the resource is excluded from caching or that the user profile last modifies changes accordingly.
       <p/>
       The server checks the correctness of the user token for <a href="../security/doc.xml">security</a> reasons.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Other headers">
      <Body>
        For the client side header it is also possible to define the response header value of value of cache-directive with the <code>cache-response-directive</code> parameter.
        See sample for no-cache below.
        The response will have the <a href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec14.html#sec14.9">HTTP Cache-Control</a> header be set accordingly.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Session Scope Caching">
      <Body>
        The WrsServlet can be bound to <code>/bcdui/servletsSessionCached/WrsServlet/*</code> URL, when working with BCD-UI models you can point them explicitely to that URL (or any other
        containing infix <code>/servletsSessionCached/</code> ) to make the framework add a <code>sessionHash</code> parameter to the URL for data request calls. You may also
        add that <code>sessionHash</code> parameter yourself, i.e. for your custom servlets. The hash is stored in <code>bcdSessionHash</code> session attribute.
        Having session specific URL you can now facade it behind the ClientCachingFilter. The data on that URL will always refresh for every new session or earliest at setting
        of ClientCachingFilter. The <code>sessionHash</code> is also stored in <code>bcdui.config</code> object in JS scope.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
  </Chapter>

  <Chapter title="Server side caching" type="api">
    <Body>
      In some cases server side caches make sense, for example to cache a standard country report shown to many users on application entry.
      It can be can be combined with client side caching.
    </Body>

    <SubChapter title="ServerCachingFilter configuration">
      <Body>
        The ServerCachingFilter will cache all responses to resources it is assigned to on a defined store for later requests.
        BCD-UI supports the file system based store out of the box.
        <br/>
        User can easy add a custom store for handle caches.
        For this issue the interface de.businesscode.soa.web.cacheControl.IServerCachePersist must be implemented.

        In order to enable server side caching the cache store must be defined.
        <br/>
        The store must be defined as a JNDI resource within the context.xml file and must have the name "BCD-UI/ServerCacheControl".
        <br/>
        <xml>
          <Resource name="BCD-UI/ServerCacheControl"
              auth="Container"
              type="de.businesscode.soa.web.cacheControl.FileCachePersist"
              absoluteFolderPath="E:\cacheTest"
              factory="org.apache.naming.factory.BeanFactory"
          />
        </xml>
        The same way you can define your oun cache store.
        <br/>
        The expires parameters follow the format given above and define when the server side cache is to be cleaned.
        This can be used to cache heavy requests being served identically to many users.
        To achieve this, add the following to to web.xml
        <xml>
          <filter>
            <filter-class>de.businesscode.soa.web.cacheControl.ServerCachingFilter</filter-class>
            <filter-name>DefaultServerCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <init-param>
              <param-name>ExpiresAbsTime</param-name>
              <param-value>00:00:00</param-value>
            <init-param>
            </init-param>
              <param-name>pattern</param-name>
              <param-value>.. full URLs including request document, space or new line separated ..</param-value>
            </init-param>
          </filter>
          <filter-mapping>
            <filter-name>DefaultServerCacheFilter</filter-name>
            <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
          </filter-mapping>
        </xml>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
    <SubChapter title="Explicitly triggered cache drop">
      <Body>
        In addition to the configured expires, it is possible to trigger a drop of the server side caches.
        This is achieved by a GET request with a <code>bcd:clearServerCache</code> parameter, sample: <code>/contextRoot/anyCachedResource?bcd:clearServerCache=cacheFilterName</code>,
        where <code>anyCachedResource</code> is a resource path the filter is mapped for and <code>cacheFilterName</code> is the logical name of the filter instance given in web.xml.
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>
  </Chapter>

</Doc>