<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../_generator/doc.xslt" media="screen" ?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010-2017 BusinessCode GmbH, Germany

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<Doc title="Client infrastructure" xmlns="http://www.businesscode.de/schema/bcdui/doc-1.1.0">
  <Chapter title="Page live-cycle">
    <Body>
      In the BCDUI library client pages are normal HTML pages. 
      The HTML page - the <i>carrier page</i> - loads the JavaScript file containing
      the BCDUI's' js and css code. Then the execution of the client-side code starts.<br/>
      The typical live-cycle of a BCD-UI page is as follows:

      <dl>
        <dt>Page loading phase:</dt>
        <dd>
          <ol>
            <li>The carrier html page is loaded by the browser</li>
            <li>BCD-UI live-cycle components on the client are constructed.</li>
            <li>The well-known guiStatus model holding information of the user's selection like chooser settings is initialized
                from the guiStatus parameter of the pages's URL</li>
            <li>Renderer on the page responsible for building the visible parts like widgets, edit grids and reports execute.</li>
            <li>The renderer ask their input and parameter <i>data provider</i> to execute, i.e. to get ready.</li>
            <li>Models, storing DOM data, are the most frequent data providers, potentially depending on other data providers as input.
                Thus, the <b>data providers form dependency trees</b> which execute recursively.
                I.e. on execute(), each data provider first checks whether the providers it depends on are ready and otherwise <i>execute</i> them.
                Only once all needed input and parameter data providers have become ready, a model proceeds the execution and becomes ready itself.
                See <a href="#Data providers">data providers</a> chapter below for more details.</li>
            <li>Some models send on execute an http GET or POST request to the server.
                This can be any URL for a static file for example or a <a href="../xmlData/doc.xml">request document</a> to WrsServlet.
                When constructing the request document, the guiStatus can be accessed this is the place where choosers settings stored on giuStatus become request filters.</li>
            <li>On server side for each request, the web services evaluate the request documents and consult the binding definitions for the appropriate places in connected databases.
                The <a href="../binding/doc.xml">binding sets</a> translate the requested logical data ids into physical databases, views, tables and columns.</li>
            <li>On server side for each request, once the web services have retrieved the data it is sent back to the client models</li>
            <li>The renderer calculate their associated views and display them on the page to the user.</li>
          </ol>
        </dd>

        <dt>Page interaction phase:</dt>
        <dd>
          <ul>
            <li>The user can use widgets and views to provide input and settings.</li>
            <li>Each activity of the user results in some change of a model.
                Usually, changes to business data are stored in the assigned data model.
                Changes to the UI, like chooser settings or sorting lead to changes in the guiStatus model.</li>
            <li>Please note, no change of model data triggers any change of the view per se.
                Instead the models will inform their listeners, if any, about the change and a renderer refresh can be triggered by the listener.</li>
            <li>A save event will cause a model to send its data to the associated web-service, usually WrsServlet which then stores the data into the database.
                Other activities like in-place drill down will lead to additional data being loaded.</li>
          </ul>
        </dd>

        <dt>Page leaving phase:</dt>
        <dd>
          <ul>
            <li>Pressing apply, menu navigation and drill-over events will cause the browser to leave the page.</li>
            <li>The apply action will in addition append the current guiStatus as a parameter to the called URL, thus the new page will initialize its settings according to the chooser of the calling page.</li>
          </ul>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </Body>
  </Chapter>

  <Chapter title="The guiStatus singelton">
    <Body>
      BCD-UI instantiates a well-known <code>guiStatus</code> data provider in each page loading phase.
      The guiStatus is a standard simpleModel but is object of the following extra-handling:
      <ul>
        <li>It has a fixed name, which is always <i>guiStatus</i></li>
        <li>It is initialized by BCD-UI during page load with the guiStatus URL parameter of the page and executed.
        It is guaranteed to be <i>ready</i> when executing code in <code>bcdui.core.ready()</code>.
        Access it as all data providers via <code>bcdui.wkModels.guiStatus</code></li>
        <li>It is the default target model for widgets</li>
        <li>It is an implicit parameter to all transformation XSLT, where it can be access with <code>&lt;xsl:param name="guiStatus"/></code></li>
        <li>The <i>apply</i> action appends its content to the url of the called page</li>
        <li>Base64 encoding is used to make it URL friendly and it is compressed to prevent it from exceeding IE's URL length restriction</li>
        <li>On server side it is decompressed and decoded by a filter and provided via <code>getHttpRequest().getAttribute("guiStatusDoc");</code></li>
      </ul>
    </Body>
  </Chapter>

  <Chapter title="Data providers">
    <Body>
      One main concept on client side of the BCDUI library are <i>data providers</i>.
      All these objects offer a getData() method returning their data (XML, String etc.), which can be used by other objects.
      In case of a Renderer, the resulting HTML is written into the DOM tree element.
      Data providers are implemented as JavaScript objects and can be easily created with the help of the bcdui.factory package or with tags.
      See more details of the live cycle, states and execution of data providers below.
    </Body>

    <SubChapter title="Available data providers">
      <Body>
        This is the list of available data providers and their action on <code>execute()</code> to become <i>ready</i>.
        <dl>
          <dt>Model</dt>
          <dd>A DOM model receiving a URL to load the XML data from the server. Can be provided a <a href="../xmlData/doc.xml">request document</a> to contact the WrsServlet.
              Please note that due to lack of DOM events in browsers you need to fire the event explicitly if you modify a model's xml with DOM methods.
              If it is in autoRefresh mode, it will reload whenever the request document changes. Auto-refresh mode is use-full for small models.</dd>
          <dt>StaticModel</dt>
          <dd>A DOM model receiving a static XML either as DOM or serialized as content</dd>
          <dt>ModelUpdater</dt>
          <dd>Applies an XSLT on a input model and replaces the target model's content with the transformation result.</dd>
          <dt>Renderer</dt>
          <dd>Executes an XSLT on a input model and inserts the result as HTML into the page at the targetHtmlElement.
              The input model is not changed.
              The transformation XSLTs can be given as a url to a single xslt, as a Chain of XSLTs or as a Model.
              In js you can also provide an array of XSLT URLs, which is then internally converted into a chain.</dd>
          <dt>ModelWrapper</dt>
          <dd>Is a sibling of Renderer with the difference of providing the result as an XML model. For the rest see Renderer.</dd>
          <dt>ConstantDataProvider</dt>
          <dd>Holds a simple data type String|Number|Boolean</dd>
          <dt>PromptDataProvider</dt>
          <dd>Prompts the user for a string input.</dd>
          <dt>DataProviderWithXPath</dt>
          <dd>Gets a source data provider and an xPath and provides the evaluated xPath.</dd>
        </dl>
        Calling <code>execute(true)</code> on a data provider will enforce the data provider to re-execute even in it is already in ready-state.
        DataProviders inform their listeners about change events so that they can update.
      </Body>

      <SubChapter title="Internals" type="internal">
        <Body>
          Internally data providers run through a list of status, where each status transition is implemented via a method.
          Each status change is fired to all status listeners.
          Because a data provider is its own listener, in can trigger the necessary next status change in a central dispatcher.
          Once the ready-status, which is common to all data providers is reached, no further transitions is happening.
          One can call execute(true) or set another state on an object with setStatus() to re-trigger the status chain and its transitions.
          getStatus().toString() will show the data providers' current status.
        </Body>
      </SubChapter>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="States, execution and asynchronicity">
      <Body>
        <p>
          All data providers are based on states. When they are constructed they start in
          an initial state. Then the user can call the <code>execute()</code> method to
          start the process associated with the object and to move it to the <i>ready</i> state.
          Calling <code>execute()</code> is necessary for a dataProvider to perform and get ready.
          In other words, models don't provide data until they are explicitly executed.
          When calling <code>execute()</code> on a data provider, it also executes all data providers it depends on and so on and waits for them to finish executing.
          During the execution there can be any number of state transitions which end up
          in the final <i>ready</i> state. Then the process (e.g. loading an
          XML document) is finished and the data offered by the data provider is available.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <code>execute()</code> method is asynchronous,
          you need to register a call-back to continue with js code using the execution result.
          To get informed about state changes all data providers offer methods to add and
          remove status listeners. These listeners are called each time the state of the
          respective object changes.
        </p>
      </Body>
    </SubChapter>

    <SubChapter title="Object Registry">
      <Body>
        To support parallel and independent creation of objects, an <i>object registry</i> singleton is available at <code>bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.objectRegistry</code>.
        It allows to <code>$register()</code> created objects and
        to register call-backs with bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.withObjects and bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.withReadyObjects, waiting for objects being created or even being ready.
        A call bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.withReadyObjects will <code>execute()</code> all data providers as soon as they become available, i.e. registered.
        <br/>
        For users of the library it is recommended to use <code>createXXX()</code> methods of the bcdui.factory package.
        These methods handle the register process for you and also wait for all input dataProviders to be come available and ready.
        <pre>
          function() {
            bcdui.factory.createSimpleModel({ id: "myModel", url: "data.xml" });
            bcdui.factory.createModelWrapper({ id: "myWrapper", url: "createRequest.xslt", input: "myModel"});
          }
        </pre>
        The BCD-UI tag library is also using these factory methods.
      </Body>

      <SubChapter title="Explicit register">
        <Body>
          Use the factory methods whenever possible.
          In case you are not using the recommended factory level for object creation,
          you need to handle register and waiting for objects explicitly.
          No matter whether the model is loaded faster or the xslt chain of the renderer, the renderer waits for its input to become ready.
          Note that on js level library objects assume the existence of all parameter objects is assumed.
          You need to use <code>bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.withObjects()</code> before using an object as an argument.
          But objects of the library still will call <code>execute()</code> on the objects they depend on an wait for them to become ready.
          <pre>
            function() {
              bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.registerObject(new bcdui.core.SimpleModel({ id: "myModel", url: "data.xml" });
              bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.withObjects({
                ids: [ "myModel" ],
                fn: function() {
                      bcdui.factory.objectRegistry.registerObject(new bcdui.core.TransformationChain({
                        id: "myRenderer",
                        chain: chainModel,
                        dataProviders: [ "myModel" ],
                        targetHTMLElementId: "contentDiv"
                      });
                    }
              }); // withObjects
            }
          </pre>
        </Body>
      </SubChapter>
    </SubChapter>
  </Chapter>

</Doc>
